WWW.MY-SUBS.COM
Would you like to come for dinner?
And then... stay all night?
Miss Lister's been
playing some impenetrable game.
My brother and I thought that
you might be more reasonable.
Oh, you mean softer?
Now you know me better.
- She's a fella.
- You're drunk, Sowden.
Thomas, I want you to
take your father home,
and then I want you to come back.
You're going nowhere!
You said a hungry pig will
eat anything and everything.
Miss Walker might make
a companion for me.
I don't want you to be hurt.
You're playing with fire.
I have defended that woman
ever since she was in her teens.
Ever since she began staying
with her aunt and uncle at Shibden Hall,
I have defended her
against the vilest insults
and innuendo, through thick and thin,
because I never once
thought any of it was true,
because I was fond of her.
And, of course, now I
realize only too vividly
what a laughingstock I've been.
- Good Lord.
- I told them.
I said, "You're playing with fire."
Your cousin laughed as I left.
I could hear her. She laughed.
- Are you sure?
- Yes.
Do you think I could make
up something like that?
Two men were hanged outside York Jail
- just three months ago...
- I know.
In front of a crowd of 6,000 people
for unnatural acts.
I know. I know that.
You mustn't repeat it
to anyone, any of it, ever.
- Why?
- Because you can't let yourself,
either of us,
or my cousin, Miss Walker,
be associated with that sort of talk.
I didn't do anything.
Anne Lister is clever.
She'll twist it. She'll turn it.
She'll make it reflect more
badly on you than on herself.
She could run rings
around Lord Grey and his cabinet
if she got anywhere near them.
She did try to deny it,
even in the room,
as though it was all in my imagination.
The best thing, the only response,
is to be rather more cool in future,
to establish some distance,
and certainly not to refer
to them in company.
The thing is,
about not mentioning it to anyone,
I was at Stoney Royd a few days ago,
and so I may have mentioned it
to elderly Mrs. Rawson.
I did... mention it
And Mrs. Stansfield
Rawson, she was there, too,
with Miss Catherine
and Miss Delia Rawson.
And then to your Aunt Ann at Cliffhill.
So I'm afraid...
yes,
it has been mentioned.
♪ Gentleman Jack 1x04 ♪
Most Women Are Dull and Stupid
- Synced and corrected by Firefly -
- www.MY-SUBS.com -
- To York?
- Yesterday.
In your cousin's carriage.
- Both of them?
- Why?
To consult a doctor about her spine
and her... nerves.
Nervy... nerve business.
She has a doctor here.
Miss Lister's line was that Dr. Belcombe
is "no provincial quack."
Dr. Kenny is a very properly
trained medical man.
It's an excuse to get
her away from her family
and on her own.
The unspoken, William,
is not always the unknown.
She'll have her in
Paris before we know it.
Would you like a posy?
Uh-oh.
Dr. Belcombe will be here in 20 minutes.
- Oh.
- Oh, Ann, no.
She's getting dressed.
It was good of you to see her
at such short notice, Steph.
Ah.
Well, I've examined her, and
we've had a good long chat
about her family and so forth.
I can give her something
for the pain in her back,
but its root cause is nervous hysteria.
Does that mean it's all in her head?
That's not to dismiss it, of course,
and I've explained this to her.
Mental suffering is just as acute
as physical suffering, but of course,
we can't see it in the same way
that we can see physical suffering,
so we tend to dismiss it.
She's had a lot of sadness
to contend with in her life.
We all cope with things
in different ways, of course.
Some people are better equipped
to deal with it than others.
Hmm.
Tell me what I can do to help.
I think you're doing it, Anne.
I think you're probably the best thing
that's ever happened to her.
She says she feels like
a fraud now she's here,
because she's felt so different
since you befriended her.
Did you say you were
thinking of traveling abroad?
Yes.
Well, then if you can persuade her,
it'll do her more good than
anything I can prescribe.
Oh, she wants to go.
Well, then that's half the battle.
Have you heard from my sister lately?
Yes.
Yes, I wrote to her,
told her we were coming to see you.
What scintillating
chitchat from Miss Lister?
Oh, she's in York.
She's taking someone to see Steph...
one of her neighbors, a Miss Walker.
A Miss Walker?
Of course.
Is there no end to Miss
Lister's selflessness?
Must've shaken you, William.
The accident above the
hall the other week.
Yes, ma'am. It wasn't pleasant.
The little boy lost a leg. Did you hear?
Sounds like the idiot driving the gig
didn't know how to handle the thing.
Couldn't say, ma'am.
It all happened so fast.
You were facing him, as I understand it,
as he approached.
Like I say,
it was all over and done with
before we knew what was going on.
James Mackenzie told me
that just after it happened,
you said you recognized
the man driving the gig
as Mr. Christopher Rawson.
They're my tenants... the Hardcastles.
They're my people,
and I'd like to know the truth.
Both my brothers work
for Mr. Rawson, ma'am,
and with him being
magistrate himself, it...
Well, it's not as if
it'd even do any good, is it?
There are other magistrates in Halifax.
Oh, aye, and they all p...
piss in the same pot.
Anyway, I could have been mistaken.
Could've been anyone.
Ah.
Is Eugénie all right?
Oh, she gets travel-sick. She's useless.
Oh.
Thomas?
Mr. Washington.
How's things at home?
Uh, same.
Any sign of him?
Nothing, no.
How's your mother?
It's a heck of a thing,
a fellow walking out
on his family like that.
I just wish we knew what
was happening with tenancy,
and then we'd know
what we were doing, sir.
All right, we'll have to see
if Miss Lister's had any
more thoughts on the matter
when she's back from York, won't we?
Dr. Belcombe was very pleased with me...
- Very pleased.
- And sees no reason
why I shouldn't make a full recovery.
- A full recovery.
- And not only did he say
there was no reason whatsoever
why I shouldn't travel abroad,
but he said it would do me good.
Well, Dr. Kenny said exactly
the same thing weeks ago.
Can you not see a difference
in Miss Walker already,
Miss Walker?
Well, everyone has been
asking where you were:
the Priestleys, the Rawsons,
Mr. and Mrs. Edwards at Pine Nest.
Everyone's been talking about you.
We were only gone three days.
Yes, but it wasn't like you.
That was the anxiety.
I feel...
I feel different. I feel better.
And come January,
our plan is to travel,
first across to the Continent,
then through Switzerland,
and then on to Rome.
For Easter, for the carnival.
And then back to England
and then up to Scotland
to see Elizabeth and the children.
You must never forget
your brother died in Naples.
Well, that's not...
Italy's...
I've been several times,
and I've never once felt
the least bit queasy.
Quite the opposite, in fact.
The climate at Easter
will be the perfect tonic.
It appears that you have my niece
quite under your spell, Miss Lister.
Oh?
I rather think she has me under hers.
Aren't you delighted
to see me so well, Aunt?
Well, I'm afraid
I must burst your bubble.
There's a letter for you on the desk.
It arrived two days ago.
I'm sorry. I opened it.
It was misdirected here,
and I didn't realize it wasn't for me.
Who?
It's your friend Mrs. Ainsworth.
Ann.
Ann, are you all right?
Your Uncle Edward's made some inquiries,
and apparently, she was
thrown out of an open carriage.
Here, here. Shh, shh, shh.
But they... they're coming here.
They... they're coming here next week!
Do you have any brandy
or smelling salts?
They're burying her on Monday.
Well, she's back from York,
but Miss Walker's had bad news...
a bereavement...
so she's staying over
there with her tonight.
Oh, dear.
Thank you, Eugénie.
And before I forget,
before she does come back,
just to warn you,
after you went off to Market Weighton,
I did... I might have...
The name of Mr. Abbott
may have escaped my lips.
- What?
- In front of Anne.
Oh!
No, it was an accident. It slipped out.
I played it down. And I'm sure...
There's nothing wrong with
you seeing someone, Marian.
If you want to invite someone to tea,
you invite someone to tea.
But, Jeremy, he makes carpets.
He's a founder member
of the Joint Stock
Halifax Banking Company.
Our father's father's father
was a wool merchant.
She forgets that.
She conveniently forgets
that when she's doing her,
"15 generations
and between two and three centuries,
all the way back to Charlemagne."
Trade.
We are descended from trade,
just like the rest.
Love, you all right?
Come here. Shh.
Come on, let's sit you down.
I'll get you some tea...
with a bit of sugar.
Let's help ourselves
to a bit of sugar for you, eh?
What's up?
I'll tell you later.
I keep thinking he's gonna
come through that door
and murder us all.
Yeah.
I'm sure he has it in him.
Amy's been crying again.
Why?
Oh, happen she misses him.
God knows why. I don't.
Only I wish we knew what we were doing.
Well, she's supposed to
be back from York today,
Miss Lister, so I'll try and talk to her
when I see her.
She'll no'an help us.
You don't know.
You know, what I can't fathom
is why he'd not take
any of his things, eh?
There's a brand-new pair of boots
under that bed upstairs.
And his cart.
Why'd he not go over to the big house
and fetch his cart, eh?
Happen he's walked to Liverpool,
sneaked on board a packet,
and sailed to America.
He once told me that's what he'd do,
if he could.
When?
Years ago.
- When?
- Years ago.
No, we'll not see him again.
We were nothing but
an inconvenience to him.
Years ago.
And I never found another one.
But...
job...
my leg...
So I'm stuck here, jack-of-all-trades.
Still...
It's nice to belong somewhere.
Oh, no.
Get it all out.
What's happened?
Do you want to talk about her...
Mrs. Ainsworth?
She was...
kind.
You must have been very close to her.
Why do you say that?
Because you're so upset.
Not close like we are,
if that's what you're thinking.
It's death.
It's anything to do with death.
Terrifies me.
I wonder
if we should pay a house call
on Mr. and Mrs. Priestley.
What?
Now, this morning, first thing.
Why?
Because...
if we skulk and avoid her,
it'll look like
we have something to hide,
something to be ashamed
of, and we haven't.
We don't.
We're just two respectable women
who choose to spend time
together, and that's all.
She saw us...
kissing.
She didn't.
Well, not exactly, but the point is...
if she says anything to anyone,
which she may or may
not do... who knows...
if we carry on as normal,
as if we have nothing to hide,
it'll undermine anything
she might go around saying,
whereas if we avoid polite company,
it might reinforce the idea
that what she says
has some truth in it.
Must we do it now, today?
I always think it's better
to broach these things head-on
and deal with them.
You could tell them
how you got on in York.
Really, they ought to be delighted.
So will Mr. Ainsworth
still come for his meeting
with the church trustees?
We haven't heard anything else.
He could always stay here with us
rather than with you, if that's helpful.
Maybe I should write to him.
As one of the church trustees,
I will be meeting with him anyway.
Thank you.
And make the offer.
Such sad news.
What a shame you didn't see Miss Walker
when she'd just returned from York.
She was a different person altogether.
Weren't you?
Dr. Belcombe was...
very pleased with me.
And sees no reason why
she shouldn't make a full recovery.
And his prescription is to travel,
so...
That went well.
Did it?
Well enough.
Listen, I've got to get back to Shibden.
Oh.
I've got things to do, people to see.
- Morning.
- Morning, ma'am.
Marian.
How was Market Weighton?
Pleasant.
Good.
How's Miss Walker?
Very...
Well, she was, and then this
bereavement knocked her for six.
Jeremiah Rawson's here to see you again.
Hmm.
I've got to go into Halifax.
I'm going down a pit.
I'll come with you.
Not down the pit, just into Halifax.
I hear you've been to York.
Is that of interest to you?
Only that it would have been helpful
to have sorted this
business before you went.
To you, perhaps. To me,
as I keep telling you,
it's a matter of indifference.
The trip was all a bit last-minute.
I'm thinking of buying a new gig.
Am I right in thinking your brother
bought a new gig recently?
Yes, yes, he did.
He didn't like it, so he sent it
back to the manufacturer in Liverpool.
Not a company he'd recommend, then.
Is there a name,
so I can avoid it?
Oh, uh... I can find out.
- Would you?
- But it would be very nice
if we could settle about the coal.
- When was that?
- What?
When he sent it back.
Four, five weeks ago. Why?
So, like you,
I was at a loss to account
for the misunderstanding between us.
Why you imagine I'd sell
both beds at that price
is a mystery after I'd adumbrated
my calculations so deftly.
But with the price being so steep,
I imagined it did cover both beds.
No.
So I value the upper
bed, if you want it,
at £160 per acre.
However, I'm prepared
to make an abatement on this
and sell it to you at
£139 and ten shillings
per acre to show good faith,
but the price of the lower bed
remains the same.
I realize you'll have
to consult your brother,
but I would like an answer
before the end of the week
so I can offer it
to the other applicant,
if that's what it comes to.
Miss Lister, you do know
that my brother isn't
someone to mess with,
don't you?
Are you threatening me?
No, I'm not.
I'm telling you for your own good.
I'm sorry
that we argued before I went away.
I... I said things I regret,
and I apologize.
I don't like it when we
argue any more than you do.
No, I know that, and I'm sorry.
I know you think it doesn't
affect me, but it does.
That's why I'm apologizing.
It upsets my equilibrium.
I know. It upsets mine too,
and I'm sorry.
I'm going to Jackson's for
flannel to make drawers.
Can I get you any?
I've got a new pattern
with an improved gusset.
I can make you some if you like.
Actually, I am planning on
traveling again in February
with Miss Walker,
Aunt Anne's health permitting.
So yes,
new drawers would be useful.
You've become great
friends, you and Miss Walker.
Hmm.
If she were to move
in with me at Shibden
as my companion,
how would you feel about that?
Would she leave Crow Nest?
She says so.
She rattles around in it on her own.
Oh, I'd be delighted.
- Would you?
- Of course!
I like her, the little I've seen of her,
and... I'd be pleased for you
to be more settled.
Thank you, Marian.
There was one thing I did say
before I went off to Market Weighton
which may have overstepped the mark
but, at the same time,
wasn't entirely inaccurate.
I believe Aunt Anne has
mentioned Mr. Abbott to you.
Anne. Anne!
His name did escape her lips, yes.
I'd like to invite him to tea.
Father says I can. In fact...
- Really?
- He'd like me to.
Well, then do you need my permission?
It was more your blessing and...
an undertaking that
you'd be civil to him.
You'll find me no obstacle
to something you have
very much at heart, Marian,
as long as it's an intelligent choice,
but one would only be doing
one's duty as an elder sister
to question the pedigree
of a man who makes rugs.
Anne!
- Miss Lister!
- Mr. Holt.
I have the figures for you, ma'am,
both for sinking a new
pit at the top of the hill
and for reopening Listerwick.
What's that?
That's just an occupational hazard.
The ceiling's low in places,
and they will forget their caps,
and then they graze their skulls.
Either that, or they bust their ankles
letting the carts catch
up with their heels.
How old is...
That one? Uh...
pfft, don't know. Six, seven, eight.
It's better if they don't get too big.
Track's narrow in places and low,
so it's just easier for them all round
if they don't fill out too much.
Are you still determined
to go down there yourself, ma'am?
Keep your 'ead down, mister.
How many people do you employ?
This pit? 14.
Five men, three women, six boys,
except some of them are girls.
And how do the shifts work?
Two 12-hour shifts,
ma'am. Round the clock.
Demand is insatiable,
and of course, down
here, it don't matter
whether it's 10:00 in the morning
or 10:00 at night.
And that model would work for my pit?
Once it's sunk. This
is a horizontal shaft.
Yours would be vertical
with a winding engine,
which is what makes your setup costs
that much more expensive.
£2,000 is a lot of money.
It is indeed, ma'am,
but you'll be laughing
when profits come in
and for years to come.
So there I am, knee-deep in water,
and it struck me that
I ought to add another clause
to the lease with the Rawsons
to stop them from turning
the water back on me
when they've finished loosening my coal.
Might I ask, Miss Lister,
what is your strategy
as regards this business
with the Rawsons,
just to be clear?
I want them to know that I know
that they've been stealing my coal,
even if we can't name it as such...
- Hmm.
- And for them to pay for it fairly,
and I want them to know
that I'm not someone
who will turn a blind
eye or be intimidated,
and as soon as I can,
I shall get down there myself
and deal with them properly,
but that's going to take time.
Christopher Rawson is a bully
and an opportunist.
He's certainly no gentleman.
Doesn't surprise me they've
been stealing from your beds.
Oh, Jeremiah's decent enough,
left to his own devices,
but he's terrified of Christopher.
If anyone's equal to him, it's you.
But, uh, he will play dirty.
Word has it that he caused
the accident above the hall
where the boy lost his leg.
Five weeks ago, he had a new gig,
and then he decided very suddenly
that he didn't like it
anymore, sent it back
to the manufacturer in Liverpool.
No witnesses?
None that will testify.
Ah.
Sadly, sending a gig
back to the manufacturer
isn't really proof of very much.
No.
Oh, and another thing,
nothing to do with Christopher Rawson...
not that I know of.
I've heard a tenant disappeared.
Mm.
He's left his family behind.
Samuel Sowden, over
at Upper Sowden Farm.
I need to know what
to do about the tenancy.
Miss Lister.
- Is she...
- No, ma'am.
She's in the library.
What's the matter?
I came as quickly as I could.
I...
I've had a letter from...
Mr. Ainsworth.
And?
An account of Mrs. Ainsworth's last day
and how kind she was
to some poor people,
and then...
the accident.
I think he wants to marry me,
and I think he wants to propose to me.
Can I see it?
- What?
- The letter.
Oh, no.
What do you mean, you think
he's going to propose to you?
The intention's clear.
Can I not see it?
It's marked private.
Well, I won't tell him.
Well, he's quick off the mark,
with his wife not yet buried.
An offer of marriage...
it's not something
to be sniffed at or treated lightly,
and a curate too, a man of God!
What more could any woman want?
- You're cross.
- Am I?
I don't... I don't want to marry him.
I want to be with you.
Well, then...
No, it's...
An offer of marriage
isn't something to be sneezed at.
And obviously,
it needs some consideration.
A clergyman's wife.
And who knows? A mother...
in the fullness of time
and then maybe one day a grandmother,
and then you really would have fulfilled
your destiny on this planet as a woman.
I...
I've been so in love with you.
I always have been,
ever since the first time I saw you
when I was 18... younger!
I think the first time
I ever saw you, I was 14,
and then I knew then.
I just... I knew, and...
It's just utterly clear to me now.
So often, whenever I've thought of it,
I've just felt a repugnance
towards forming any sort
of connection with a man,
but I...
She was a lot older than him.
Sorry?
Mrs. Ainsworth, she...
she was 15 years older than him, and...
Once or twice, she would joke...
at least I always
thought it was a joke...
that she would die first, and then...
who would look after Thomas?
And she'd say, "It'll
have to be you, Annie."
Why won't you let me see the letter?
Because...
What?
I told you, it's marked private.
Anne?
You're going to have to make a decision.
There's clearly more to it
than you're able or willing to tell me.
So he will require an answer,
I assume, as much as I do
to this alleged proposal.
No, he hasn't actually asked me yet.
No,
but for some reason, it would appear
to be on the cards,
and it would be good
to have an answer ready,
so...
Ah, today's Friday.
I propose you have the weekend
to think it over, and...
instead of giving me your yes or no
on the 3rd of April,
I'd like it first thing Monday morning,
and then we both of us
know what we're doing.
I can't make such
a big decision so quickly!
Do you think I should marry him?
That...
Only you can decide something like that.
Most people
would think I'd be
foolish not to at my age,
wouldn't they?
Yes.
Yes, they would.
Would we still see each other?
No.
I think if you take him,
you'd have to give me up.
No, but not as friends.
Only as this, Anne.
How could we go back to
common friendship now?
No.
You must think it through carefully,
because you'll have to live
with the consequences,
whichever way you decide.
We both will.
And there'll be no going
back on it once it's made,
but I think it would be very unlikely
that we could remain friends
after all that's passed between us.
I think it would be too painful.
Why do I have to decide on Monday?
Because we have to
know what we're doing.
I have to know what I'm doing.
I behaved as well as I could.
Though perpetually saying to myself,
"Well, I care not how she decides;
I care not much for her;
the whole thing was only ever a game,"
as I left, she hung upon me
and cried and sobbed aloud at parting,
saying, "I hope we shall meet
under happier circumstances."
"Well," said I to myself
as I walked off,
"a pretty scene we have had,
but surely I care not much,
and I shall take my time of suspense
very quietly and be easily reconciled
either way."
Don't do this to me.
Don't you dare do this to me again.
Jeremiah tells me
you've been letting Miss Lister
run rings around you over her coal.
Christopher, is it true?
No, Mother, it isn't.
That's not exactly how
I worded it, Mother.
Maneuvering you into
paying silly prices.
Trying to and failing miserably.
- She's very clever.
- Oh, we know she's clever.
That's why I like her,
her company, her conversation,
even though she is a bit of an oddity.
She's been to so many places,
done so many things.
Most women are dull and stupid...
but not her.
Well, happily,
I'm just as clever as she is,
and I have the measure of her.
Oh, I doubt it!
Cake?
She's threatening to sink her own pits,
so she has us over
a barrel as regards price,
given what's gone on.
You haven't been stealing
her coal, have you?
What?
Nothing.
What did Stansfield say?
Nothing, Mother.
I'm fast coming to the conclusion
that she's bluffing about
sinking her own pits,
because how could she
possibly afford it?
And this latest demand is just nonsense.
I'm tempted to tell her
where she can shove her upper bed...
sorry, ladies... and call her bluff.
Well, perhaps her little
friend will help her.
She's got plenty of money.
Sorry, what? Who?
Miss Walker, your cousin!
They went to York together, apparently,
and now they're inseparable.
- Really?
- Next stop, Paris.
Maybe Miss Walker will let Miss Lister
dip into her purse.
Whatever else she's been
letting her dip into.
So sorry, ladies.
Me and the lads generally stop
for us dinners about now, Miss Lister,
if that's all right.
Yes, of course it is.
Jamie, lad.
I'll just do this, Mr. Booth.
Aye, good lad.
He's a good lad.
You should have a drop of beer,
if nowt else, for your dinner, ma'am.
You've been digging like the devil.
Mm...
Need to talk to you
about you and Eugénie.
Really is an inconvenience.
It's all off.
Sorry?
It's not happening,
so we're all all right.
- Oh.
- Yep.
What happened?
Nothing. Just, uh...
You know.
'Course, as you said,
it were a step down for her.
It would never have done,
and she realized that
when she got back from York, so...
She was very pale in York...
and tearful.
I pretended not to notice, but...
Was she pregnant?
Well, it wasn't mine.
It was George's, wasn't it?
I thought they were getting on very well
in Hastings and in Langton, and then...
Good Lord.
I thought she was
preoccupied with something
when we got back here, but...
I just couldn't decide if it was just...
you know, Shibden.
I felt sorry for her.
In a new place and
a load of unfamiliar faces,
and Mrs. Cordingley said... Cordingley?
She confided in Mrs. Cordingley,
with her having a bit of French,
and we none of us knew
what to do to help her...
Everyone?
Sorry, all of the servants knew?
And Eliz... Mrs. Cordingley
said what she needed,
what Eugénie needed,
was a man with a good Christian heart
to step in and do the decent thing.
Oh, John.
Well, it weren't
entirely a selfless thing.
I was... I am...
a bit smitten with her.
You do realize you're too
good for her, don't you?
Well, it's often the way
when you feel like that
about someone, isn't it?
It's very rare that both parties feel
exactly the same about each other.
I don't know.
I think sometimes a
thing can start that way,
but then...
Will you... you won't dismiss her,
will you?
Hmm.
Well,
proper French lady's
maids don't grow on trees,
certainly not in Halifax.
I don't know what shocks me most,
the thing itself or
Cordingley not saying anything to me.
Are you all right, ma'am?
I'm always all right.
Ma'am!
- There you are.
- Hello.
- Hello, John.
- Mr. Washington.
Young Thomas Sowden has asked me
to ask you if you've had
any further thoughts about their tenancy
since his father took off.
Yes.
I have.
Come on. Come on.
Mom.
- Mrs. Sowden?
- Yes.
It's a letter from my
father, Mr. Washington,
on behalf of Miss Lister
about your tenancy.
I like your pigs, Mrs. Sowden.
I'd like to farm pigs meself.
Just ignore her. She talks too much.
Can either of you girls read?
Thomas?
Thomas, there's a letter from
Mr. Washington about the tenancy.
Hello!
Hello.
Would you mind?
"Dear Thomas and Mrs. Sowden,
Miss Lister confirm"...
Can never read his spidery writing.
Um, "Miss Lister
confirmed this afternoon,
following a conversation
with her lawyer, Mr. Parker,
in Halifax yesterday,
that if Samuel has
not returned to the farm
within a period of two months,
as of today's date,
she will be obliged to terminate
her agreement with him
as regards to the tenancy of the farm."
What?
Hold on.
"At that point, however, she also"...
What?
"Confirms that she will offer"...
"Confirms that she will offer
a six-month tenancy to you, Thomas,
at the same price your
father pays presently."
Can I go and look at your
pigs now, Mrs. Sowden?
Of course you can. Amy,
you take this young lady...
Eliza and Suzannah.
Well, you take Eliza
to look at the pigs.
And, well, I can offer you a cup of tea
and a bit of cake, both of you.
That's very kind. Thank you.
So no sign, then, of Mr. Sowden?
No, nothing.
We're glad he's gone.
I'd take advice, obviously,
but as well as reopening Listerwick,
I'd like to sink a new pit
here, above Conery Wood.
What?
I've told you before,
it's a nasty business.
I wish you wouldn't...
Hinscliffe has heard Rawson's men
in my upper bed here,
which means they're
not just stealing coal;
they're stealing
significant amounts of coal.
What am I supposed to
do, take it lying down,
let them take what
they want from my land
and not do anything?
Is it costed?
Just over £2,000.
I believe I can get it to just under.
I can't lend you more than £450.
Really?
And how will you get the rest?
Well, it's not impossible that...
Miss Walker and I have become
very close, and if things...
How would you feel
if she were to move
in here with me as...
For Miss Lister.
My companion?
I'd be very happy for you.
It's time you settled.
All right, thank you.
Well, then...
it's not impossible that
she might be in a position
to lend me some money.
Ma'am, the servant from
Crow Nest just called
with this for you.
Thank you.
My love,
I find it impossible
to make up my own mind.
I promised you an answer,
and I'm at your mercy.
I have written the words "yes" and "no"
on a slip of paper and
put them in a purse.
If you still think it
better to decide today,
the paper you draw out
first must be the answer.
Whatever shall be the event,
I shall always remain your
faithful and affectionate
- Ann Walker.
- _
I would have known what
to do with a yes or a no,
but this?
What am I supposed to do with this?
I mean, do you think,
do you really think
that I'm someone to
have my future happiness
decided by fate,
by which bit of paper
comes out of a purse first,
like a... like a raffle ticket?
- No.
- What?
No. I... I couldn't...
What?
- Ann!
- Nothing.
I'm taking it as a no.
It isn't a no.
Well, it isn't a yes.
Will you accept him?
I don't want to, but...
But?
But what?
What?
If I did,
it would be out of duty.
Duty?
What, to her? To Mrs. Ainsworth?
No.
Well, what, then?
I...
Ann.
Ann, talk to me. We're adults.
Nothing can be this bad.
I'll never see you again.
What? What do you mean?
If I tell you the truth, you won't want
anything to do with me.
I might surprise you.
Hmm?
It's him.
Him? Him who?
The Reverend Ainsworth.
I've been...
Indiscreet with him.
He said that he was in love with me,
and that he wanted to marry
me and she wouldn't live long,
and I didn't want to,
but I didn't know how to say no.
That's why I was so upset
when I heard that she'd died,
because I knew this would happen!
I knew it wouldn't be five minutes
until he was writing to me, and, Anne,
Anne, I never encouraged him.
I told him I didn't want
to, but then he just...
managed situations that
he was alone with me,
either here when they visited
or there at their house.
Do...
do you understand?
You understand the problem?
He's had...
Intimate knowledge of me.
Intimate how?
Kissing?
Did he...
Touching?
Have you been connected?
Once.
This is the thing.
Does that not...
put me under an obligation to him,
to Mr. Ainsworth?
Hang on.
He inflicted himself on you.
You were in his house
to visit your friend, his wife.
You were under his protection,
in his house,
and he took advantage of you.
When she left the room.
But still, does...
morally, does that not...
No, God. Good God, no!
Of course it doesn't.
You're under no obligation at all
because he was married,
for heaven's sake!
You're shouting. You're cross.
No, I'm not shouting at you.
I'm not cross at you.
I'm glad... I'm glad
you've told me, Ann.
Ann, you are not obligated to him.
And do you see? Do you...
do you see now this is why
I couldn't say yes to you,
because I was worried that...
all sorts... that you'd be c... cross...
- No.
- And that you'd expose me,
and that I wasn't even free
or fit to say yes to you,
and that's why I couldn't
show you the letter,
and it's...
The letter's right here.
And it's just clear
from the language he uses
he already thinks I'm his.
To "My own little Annie,"
from "Your own Thomas Ainsworth,"
and I couldn't tell anybody
because he said it would reflect
just as badly on me as it did on him.
I know you'll think I'm weak...
and stupid...
but you see, if I'd had
someone like you in my life,
this would've never happened,
because I'd have had someone to talk to,
to tell...
someone who would've helped me.
Is everything you've
told me absolutely true?
Yes.
You do know I would have got you
out of this scrape, don't you,
whether you'd have
said yes to me or not?
Would you?
Grubby little wretch.
And in a dog collar.
He'll still be coming
over for this position,
this meeting with the church trustees.
The whole thing, no
doubt, is just a ruse
to get nearer to me.
Shh, shh, shh.
You have nothing more to fear from him.
Do you understand me?
What are you going to do to him?
I haven't decided yet.
The Reverend Thomas
Ainsworth is at the door.
You don't think he
intends to propose to you?
So you shouldn't say
anything to Mr. Ainsworth.
Miss Lister! The thing
you should understand...
What you need to understand
is you would be exposed...
as an adulterer.
If she wants to start
running with the big dogs,
then she's gonna have to
find out what it's like
when they really start biting.
You're in the worst kind of danger,
in this world and the next.
I would rather
die then people know what we do.
It's wrong! It's repugnant!
You understand nothing about me.
- Synced and corrected by Firefly -
- www.MY-SUBS.com -